okay we'll
start uh so I'm going to do a d dub dub
means when the Llama is late and they
have to do a horse race through the
material
uh I'm going to cover your homework for
tonight okay because it took me like
eight hours to write it and uh two of
the questions are linguistic you can get
it from the reading okay so two of the
questions you have to sess out on your
own it's the Chinese
nean and it's Moksha and MTI and Shanti
and you can figure it out from the
reading okay those are just uh
linguistic questions okay I'm going to
cover the three questions on your
homework which have some which have some
meat to them okay
uh first one uh I don't know about you
but when I was and and by the way I'll
stop in about half an hour and then I'm
I have the idea Swami G and me sit up
here and you got to ask us questions
okay it's really disappointing to me
when we have a visiting teacher and you
just what's that DOA uh CA when there's
everybody's CA at the same time so uh
you know ask him what his birthday is or
anything okay uh okay uh I have some
questions for you s g anyway if they
don't ask you I'll ask you but um um
when I was growing up and so we're
talking about Nirvana right and the the
goal of this week three days here and
three days in the Bahamas and Swami G
will be teaching Us in the Bahamas too
by the way there's still room there okay
you just have to get there uh some room
opened up today and there's some tents
the tents are nice unless it's a
typhoon
uh there's nice hotels around but I I
would try to come if you can it's an
amazing place
place it's one of the few uh working
celibate ashrams in the western world
and it's nice it's a beautiful place
it's a good place you should learn about
that place and you should go for yoga
vacations you know like you do five days
in a row two yoga classes a day and you
get some good SAT songs and chanting and
stuff like that you can steal their
kons uh okay so
uh when I was going oh so the point of
this week is to address our most is the
air air conditioning on up high it's
amazingly
inefficient
uh okay
anyway
uh the point of this week is that you
identify your most and I identify my we
all identify our most serious CLA and
then we work on it right uh and I I
wanted to tank I I went to Matt's yoga
class today uh he worked really well
on on uh my specialty I guess it was
just a coincidence uh but he did
jealousy and addictions then I figured I
had both and
uh by the time he was done I figured I
had both so anyway but I really liked it
and I I'm grateful to the yoga teachers
and uh I'm hoping Swami G will continue
that in the Bahamas
and maybe some creas or pranama that
would affect those DOA
types uh so I'm asking him to help us uh
cuz they're really good at it frankly
the Tibetans have it but they those
practices were not emphasized and they
were partly lost you can read them in
books but you don't have monks going
around doing a lot of prama okay so it's
kind of a nice marriage that we have all
right
um
so I wanted to talk about uh when I was
growing up there was this uh perception
about Nirvana right or the reason they
call certain bars Nirvana bar or uh they
call bands
Nirvana and uh the idea is that somehow
Nirvana is some mindless Bliss out state
right and uh that you kind of meditate
for a long time and then suddenly you
slide into Nirvana and you're in this
mindless Bliss out State and you kind of
disappear you melt into it that's kind
of the feeling and that's why I think
they call a lot of bars Nirvana because
people do that and uh I don't know about
you but I I grew up hearing that kind of
thing so I thought I would like to
address that you know in two parts uh
first of all is there any historical
basis for that idea you know is that
just a crazy idea or or did it come from
someplace real and then uh I would
say well let's start with
that is there such a thing in Buddhist
history and then secondly did anybody
object to that idea in Buddhist history
okay was was there anybody who taught
that and what was the reaction of the
rest of Buddhism okay
um and there is a thing uh in the Abid
Dharma schools so there are four Great
Schools of ancient
India uh and and they are a ladder you
go up the schools and you get more
sophisticated and more
correct but the Buddha taught all four
schools okay the a lot of the ideas of
the first school contradict the other
schools and and it goes like that you
see Buddha himself gave teachings that
were
contradictory because some people would
some people would be attracted to school
number one and they would benef they
would benefit even though it wasn't a
full explanation and then some people
then they would graduate to school
number two School number three School
Number Four okay so all four schools
were taught by Lord Buddha but they're
three of them are incorrect three and a
half of them are incorrect okay
technically but they're useful it's a
good place to start okay so the lowest
school is called uh chatma or viasa
you can call them ABI Dharma School uh
ABI Dharma means higher
knowledge ABI Dharma is a system of
ancient India that was sort of
encyclopedic and they took old sutras
and they made extremely dry boring books
out of them I know because my first 10
years in the monastery I worked on
it
uh I I kind of worked backwards you know
so they made me do Abid Dharma it was
incredibly
dry okay and anyway they have an idea of
n Nirvana they call I want you to say
the word okay it's very famous in band
it's called B
Rick
Rick p pambo pambo means your physical
body
uh sometimes particulate
matter um living matter are made of
molecules physical body okay P Pam
Rick uh Rick means your mind the stream
of your mind mind Stream So bam is the
stream of your physical body and Rick is
your your stream of your
thoughts gun means the stream cha means
suddenly
stops okay and that's their definition
of
nirvana okay so there is a school the
lowest School in ancient in India called
Abid Dharma and they said Nirvana was b
g then you practice and practice and
practice and then suddenly you're not
there anymore just suddenly you stop
terminate okay body and mind are
discontinued it's called discontinued
okay why did they think that uh because
Lord Buddha said in a couple of places
that uh you reach a place where you have
nothing left and then in a couple of
places he said you stop the C corlo The
Wheel of Life right and in your reading
I think you have a drawing of The Wheel
of Life somewhere in this reading what
page is it on page 14
okay when Lord Buddha taught the uh C
Coro The Wheel of Life that
drawing uh he said if you are when you
reach nirvana you have stopped the wheel
of rebirth so the Abid dharmas scho
thought oh he meant we just disappear
you know somehow we just stop and that's
Nirvana right and then I don't know
about you but it just seemed like a
weird goal to me you know uh like what
do I do after that who's going to feed
my cat you know uh you know like it just
seemed like a weird uh go I was never
comfortable with that and they taught it
to me and I was never comfortable with
it and then um the higher schools debate
against the Abid Dharma schools they say
uh
so uh is there such a thing as an arhat
right arhat means someone who has
achieved Nirvana right arhat means foe
Destroyer destroyer of the enemy arhan
right and then they they ask a question
has these people have they achieved
Nirvana yes that's what an Arad is have
they what enemy have they defeated what
do you think think the Claus okay the
enemy is the Claus a synonym for someone
who has reached nirvana is a CLA
destroyer and that Swami G was talking
about that I liked it
uh so the higher schools ask the Abid
Dharma school has anyone ever achieved
Nirvana yes what do you call them arot
enemy destroyers yeah what do they look
like where are they you know then
they're like well there's lots of AR
Hawks yeah but
B their mind sto their body sto where
where are they you know who are they
show me a arot you know so then they get
stuck it seems like a dumb place to be
right I don't
know uh and they get stuck and then they
can't answer uh the higher schools say
of course that um the definition of
nirvana is
uh
it's just the condition of having elimin
Swami G said eradicated it's a very good
word uh eradicate to rip out from its
root the Claus okay when you no longer
have any claes at all then you have
reached nirvana and that's Nirvana okay
so the higher schools disagree with the
Abida SK but you will hear it in certain
countries uh like uh Sri Lanka uh
Thailand uh Burma those three countries
because only the Abid dama reached those
countries the other schools didn't reach
those countries uh so they were very
early they became Buddhists very early
and then it got cut off and they didn't
get the rest of the schools so you will
hear stuff like that that you reach a
place where you are nothing anymore and
uh we don't agree with that all right
it's not what Nirvana
is I think whenever someone describes
what is nirvana or what is Enlightenment
you have to question does it help people
okay is it of use to other people you
know can I serve people if I reach that
I was in college they taught us
uh the somebody in my college said the
test of a religion is what would some
Professor when I was in college and they
said the test of a religion is what
would happen if everybody was doing it
you see what I mean uh so recently we
had an incident some person said uh they
stabbed another person and they said
they had a they were having a tantric
experience but then you have to ask the
question what would happen if everyone
was doing that you know now I mean if
that was a real useful thing then you
have to ask what would happen if
everybody was doing that you see what I
mean uh and that would be sort of Chaos
uh and then everybody would be
inip all right
automatic uh so
uh it's not like that okay then when you
reach nirvana it has to be a state which
is very useful to other people and which
serves other people and Enlightenment is
even further than that okay so that's
the basic idea that's one question I
wanted you to hear okay uh
then uh a person from India last night
asked me a question about Nirvana they
said when I was young in India uh near
Mumbai uh what they taught us was that
Nirvana is the end of rebirth okay
Nirvana means you no longer have to take
rebirth okay and then she asked me is
that what Nirvana means right and you
hear that also okay you can say uh n is
the end of The Wheel of Life so I what
page four there's a drawing page
14 uh those readings are going to get
shorter I'll tell you that um I'm
running out of time uh but you can see a
wheel okay on page
14 uh it's good I'm good uh this wheel
was designed by Lord Buddha himself all
right and a lot of you had had have had
that teaching on that wheel um
uh and there there were two instances in
his life when he when he created this
drawing and in the drawing is
summarized uh the suffering of Life the
six forms of suffering in life
so sometimes they are six sections
Midway through the wheel not the very
center but the next thing
out uh there are you can see Realms and
if you look closely you can see animals
or you can see spirits or you can see
hell beings or like that so this is a
summary of the Six States of rebirth
there are six forms in which you can be
reborn okay
uh the three better ones are called
human and
assur and DEA so the
Tibetans translated DEA as worldly
pleasure beings pleasure beings powerful
temporary States of
pleasure Heavenly temporary heavens and
they say they say it's a very bad place
to be cuz you get
lazy and then you die
terribly uh you you have a you have a
very beautiful life and then you die
terribly okay that's they're not
enlightened they they are worldly deas
okay I I call them pleasure beings then
Aur means uh almost pleasure beings and
and they like to fight with the pleasure
beans because they are consumed by
jealousy so that's a famous war that
goes on sometimes the ga is interpreted
as the war between you know the deavas
and the asuras anyway so these are three
better births then there's a hell hell
Realms there's a guy named TS what's his
name CS Lewis you should read his books
he wrote a beautiful book called the
screw tape letters you could read it
okay screw tape letters very short very
beautiful and uh it's a discussion
between the devil and his
nephew uh and and he said he had almost
went crazy writing it because he had to
put himself in the devil's head he wrote
it from the devil's point of view and uh
it's an intense uh is that he's got a
copy that's so funny uh okay it's it's
short and it's sweet and it's powerful
okay that the devil sends his nephew to
corrupt a young man in England in the
1940s okay so uh but in that book The
Devil says one of our greatest
achievements in modern times is That No
One Believes In Hell anymore they think
uh it's not real they think there's no
such place you know they think it's just
some kind of uh you know hangover you
had once or you know they interpret it
as some small thing happening in this
world it's not true okay and that's
another subject and we can talk about it
someday but the Realms of hell are
pictured in that in that okay and then
there are Realms of spirits uh sort
of uh tormented Spirits okay like what
they say what do you when uh ghosts in a
haunted house or something like that so
anyway there are six different Realms
animal Realm six different ways you can
take birth okay so some people have
called Nirvana the end of the end of
rebirth you you got out of this circle
okay I think if you look up if you look
carefully on the upper right hand side
who's is there anything
there there's Lord Buddha he's pointing
to the moon on the other side upper left
hand corner is there a big
circle yeah so uh he's pointing to
Nirvana okay but he not in the wheel
he's outside the wheel okay that's the
idea of that
[Music]
painting so they're not used to have
trouble with that you know somebody says
oh you know uh the definition of nirvana
is you get to escape the wheel of
rebirth you know and I'm like well first
of all I was brought up in a country
where we didn't believe in rebirth so
that doesn't impress me so much you know
what I mean no I mean I'm not so worried
about being a bug next life U my mom
didn't believe in next life you either
go to heaven or you go to hell and
that's it you don't have to worry about
bugs you know I mean that's how I was
brought up and and so it didn't impress
me much and then my llamas would press
me you oh you got to escape the wheel of
rebirth and then I'm like well what's
going to happen to me after that you
know if I'm not any of the different
ways a person can be what am I after
that in my b g Jaa do I just kind of
dissolve and you know like I had too
many martinis and you know I'm in the
Nirvana bar you know and and I'm just
what's happened you know it's not very
attractive to tell somebody you can
escape the wheel of rebirth and then I'm
like well where will I be what will I be
because I won't be any of the six ways
you can be and then uh what's going to
happen with my friends you see what I
mean
like to be honest I love a lot of my
friends I would like to be in my my
future lives with them you know I don't
want to end rebirth completely if it
means I can't be with my friends or my
family or people I love if you just want
me to dissolve into some corner of the
universe then uh it's not attractive to
me I I don't want to do that it's it's
not a big goal for me don't tell me that
I'm not going to work for that it's it
doesn't seem right to me these
descriptions of oh I will become an
enlightened being and serve countless
living creatures on countless planets
those attract me those are sexy you know
why are we uh why are we obsessed with
X-Men and Spider-Man and Iron Man and
Transformers and Superwoman and Wonder
Woman and
Electra what's this Tomb Raider
lady she wants Jonah AR but we don't
make she doesn't wear a good suit um
anyway you know why are
we why are we so attracted you know it's
that we want to do that all of us would
there's a deep human desire to save the
planet each person would like to be the
one you know it's a like a Jesus complex
or something you would like to be that
deep down you would like to be that you
know that's your deepest wish you make
any superhero movie it SS it makes $5
million
in the first week you know and it
they're not different from each other a
Transformer three is the same as one is
the same as five you know just endless
smashing things and
uh but we love it and we're attracted to
it I don't want a Nirvana Where I just
disappear and I'm not reborn as anything
I want to be like
a a being who operates on multiple
planets and helps people I want that I
believe in that that's what I want you
know so so then you have to explain what
did they mean when you stopped The Wheel
of Life and what does it mean to say
you're not reborn anymore and I wanted
to talk about that a little bit
okay so when I was growing up and and I
heard about
rebirth then I don't know about you all
these thoughts were uh all these
thoughts
were imprinted on our minds before age
10 or something right what is nirvana
what is karma what is rebirth so for me
rebirth meant there was a factory
somewhere in
Kansas I don't know why it was always in
the
Midwest and uh they were producing
bodies dog
bodies and uh there's an assembly line
somehow they feed them the stuff they
feed cows and uh they crank out dog
bodies and they have little trap doors
in the back on the back and then Spirits
people die on the east coast and then
Spirits kind of wafted over the country
and then somebody grabs them a spirit
and shoves it into the trap door in the
back of a dog and then they slam and
then you're reborn into a dog that's the
image I had in my I think yours is
similar I bet it's similar
you just don't want to admit it uh no
it's like oh my spirit will go and get
caught in a in another animal or
something like that okay that's how we
think about
rebirth okay so we talk about this
countless times right we count we talk
about this countless
times
so all the things around me in according
to our belief are tiny images that are
popping out of karmic vasana
seeds uh and and I don't really see a
pen right there's a A vasana or a seed
karmic seed in in my subconscious it
pops open a tiny image of a pen comes
out what do we we said self-illuminating
right it it is Lumin
image and then my
mind slaps it onto this cylinder and
then I see it as a pen okay and if I had
not planted that seed I might see it as
a chew toy something to chew okay uh how
did that seed get planted in my mind I
offered a pen to another person you can
only plant a seed a vasana with another
person or a
sansara you can only plant it with
another person you must offer an a
writing instrument to another person and
you must observe yourself you must
witness yourself doing it and in that
moment that you let go of the writing
instrument and give it to another person
in that moment your mind records the
event as a karmic seed and then you know
couple weeks later gishi Michael's hand
goes into his vest pocket
you know that's why Lord Buddha made
this
bucket uh and
uh and the Hand comes out and in that
millisecond a karmic seed opens in your
mind it produces a small luminous image
and it slaps it on the cylinder and you
see a pen but if if you
had planted a different seed right like
giving uh dogs things to chew
okay then you would have a different
seed you'd have a seed in your mind and
and I would pull this thing out and you
would start
drooling okay
uncontrollably uh cuz you want to chew
on it okay now I'm going to say
something very important and don't
forget it okay I'm going to say
something important and don't forget
it if the karmic seed that opens in your
mind makes you want makes you have an
uncontrollable desire desire to chew
this pen you have been reborn as a
dog and that's all there is to being
reborn okay there's no dog factory
making bodies and and you get your
spirit gets locked into a dog's body
that was already there it's not there's
no such
thing rebirth means the seeds in your
mind to see this object as a pen wear
out
new seeds are waiting behind them those
are seeds for seeing it as a chew toy
and wanting to chew on it desperately
okay when the seeds to see out as a pen
wear out and when they are replaced by
seeds waiting behind them to see it as a
pen you is a
dog got it and it can happen in 10
seconds okay you don't have to get hit
by a
are okay it's it's very if you truly
understand where the world is coming
from rebirth becomes an issue it becomes
a frightening issue it takes 10 seconds
to become a dog and you won't
know because you won't remember because
you won't even have enough karmic seeds
to remember what you were 10 seconds ago
and you will be a
dog okay and they can't get enlightened
easily they can't think they can't come
to Swami G's talks got it seriously you
know you have a you know if you really
grasp why you're seeing yourself as a
human it's
frightening it's very frightening and
you suddenly you become very spiritual
person it'll wear off by the time we
leave um but uh no I mean it does it
wears off
but it's not like you have to believe in
some Asian idea about you might be a
cockroach in your next life you know
it's not that it's that the way you're
perceiving your arm your hand right now
is coming from seeds in your mind from
having given things to other people
charity Donna right and if those seeds
wear out which they will then then seeds
waiting behind it might make you see a
paw and then you is a
dog okay that's what it is to be a dog
and you won't remember what you were 5
minutes before that you you'll feel like
you've always been a dog and you won't
be able to think clearly you you will be
a dog okay it's very frightening okay so
now what does it mean to escape the
wheel of rebirth okay now it's a
different now it's a different ball game
right uh when you understand well enough
how karmic seeds produce your world and
you start acting on that regularly for
example with screaming bosses or
Partners they yell at
you under the influence of this
training you look at them you know by
the way the reaction of a well-trained
spiritual person to an angry person is
like
this
cuz they're trying to remember when did
I plant that seed like this is the most
insulting thing you can do at our at our
asham someone yells at you and you
go like you don't say anything back to
them you're just
like and that means how did I create
this idiot you know like uh you know
what did I do it's worse than getting
angry back you know it's a big insult
you say you're a fool and the person
goes you're like how did I create this
person when did I call somebody a fool
recently there a a well-trained
spiritual person is always going around
like you know why how did I make this
person like that you know and then they
they their vision is automatically
directed to their own heart what did I
do to make this person like that okay
uh as you get better at thinking like
that you destroy your negative emotions
your claas that destroys your claas
because you don't get angry back and you
get out of the habit of getting angry
back it's what Swami G said about
hitting a pillow it's dangerous to get
angry
once because you'll get in the habit of
of of getting angry and then that's hard
to get out of the Habit right so as you
get better
you react more and more to negative
people and things with
this and then you reach a point where
you stop reacting negatively at all okay
because it doesn't help anything it's
wrong it creates new irritating
people understanding overcomes your
negative emotions okay got it only
understanding in our system nothing else
can stop anger and nothing nothing else
can stop jealousy everything else is a
Band-Aid everything else is a Band-Aid
you can say don't get mad at your boss
don't get mad at your partner it's
unpleasant it gives you a what do you
call ulcer it gives you a heart attack
but in the
end it would create weird seeds in your
mind and you might
be your old seats are wear out and
suddenly you're surrounded by 10,000
screaming vicious people that's called
hell you see what I mean because you
kept getting angry at people you see
what I mean so there's an interesting
thing and it's the same in the yoga
Sutra in the fourth chapter what is it
uh Karma
Shukla uh a yogi for a yogi karmas are
neither black nor
white
uh are there are three kinds tree withd
them
uh in the fourth chapter of the yoga
Sutra they are talking about the process
the point which you reach in your life
where your understanding of where stuff
is coming from is so strong that it
prevents old karmic seeds from opening
they can't open okay technically you
don't get rid of them they are sitting
there in your Storehouse Consciousness
aive of isana
uh they are staying in you you have them
billions upon billions of karmic seeds
are waiting in your heart
chakra
uh but when you reach a point of
understanding they can't open anymore it
short circuits them it's it's in the
fourth chapter the yoga sura it's very
beautiful you will never have to pay
back those
debts
uh okay it's very interesting that's
Nirvana okay the most subtle claa the
final clure to go is a Vidia and it's
the source of all other ones okay if you
can
destroy your misunderstanding of your
screaming
partner by this
okay that means you're getting close
Okay like you don't respond anymore
they're like I'm yelling at you and
you're like yeah I know you know I'm
just trying to figure out where the heck
you came from from you know and uh you
know as your reaction gets more and more
like that a Vidia starts to disappear
when a viia when the subtlest form of a
viia is gone old karmic seeds cannot
open
anymore so what happens to the dog
rebirth you use up the seeds to see this
as a pen they wear
out that's by the way why pens run out
of ink pens don't run out of ink no pen
has ever run out of ink okay the person
using the pen ran out of seats you have
to understand that it's very profound
you know no car ever broke nobody ever
got
old okay it's just seeds wore out in
your mind okay it's nothing else so
what's going to happen if if I have
reached a certain level
of understanding that I can't get angry
anymore cuz I'm too still worried about
I'm still think I'm too much thinking
about where the hell they came from what
did I do last week to make this person
right the seeds to see this as a pen
have worn out new seeds cannot open new
new old Bad Seeds cannot open even new
old good seeds can't open nothing none
of the old seeds can open so what
happens then
you know that's the end of rebirth okay
there's no uh seeds left to be
anything
else cuz they can't
open okay they can't open then then the
wheel has stopped and rebirth has
stopped am I
gone okay my pan seeds were out I can't
have any other seeds do suddenly
everything disappear in my life no there
are a third set of
seeds there's old bad karmas there's old
good karmas and then there's pure
karmas okay there's old good karmas
there's old bad karmas and then there's
pure karmas okay then the pure karmas
kick in and they create a a body of
light uh it's very beautiful okay so the
the answer to the Coan is do you stop
The Wheel of Life when you reach
nirvana yeah why your your understanding
is so powerful that old good seeds and
old Bad Seeds can't open anymore you
cannot be born again as a human does
that mean I just disappear no cuz
there's other kinds of seeds in you
called Pure seeds Okay what are pure
seeds pure seeds are good seeds planted
by conscious understanding of where
stuff comes from got
it okay the seeds like here
watch the good seeds planted by trying
to figure out where the heck your
partner's anger came from tonight are
pure seeds and they create a body of
light okay so how does that differ from
a impure good seed impure good seed is
like they yell at you you never had any
training
you're like oh I'll try to be patient
with them you know they're unpleasant I
shouldn't fight I'll try to be patient
for them that's a good dirt we call a
dirty Good Karma s a dirty Good Karma
it's a good karma but it's dirty why you
don't understand they came from you
you're just trying to be nice it it
doesn't involve understanding that they
came from you you're just trying to be
nice to them that's a dirty Good Karma
what makes it
dirty you didn't you're not responding
out of knowledge you're responding out
of uneducated goodness which is
dangerous it's very interesting so
you'll make a dirty Good Karma so what's
the difference between a pure Good Karma
and a dirty Good Karma dirty good karmas
wear
out pure good karmas don't wear out
he that's interesting you see like uh if
you have a
relationship and uh it's going well for
six months Swami G talked about it and
then it starts to fall apart they all
start to fall apart if they start to
fall apart it's a sign that that
relationship is coming from Dirty good
karmic seeds okay and if you understood
how to create pure karmic seeds you
could have an enlightened relationship
this is something cool okay then I'll
stop and we'll have question answer Lord
Buddha
on the night you want the real
story okay uh it's called sulba sulba
means his all that stuff under the bodh
tree at Bood Gaia and the demons came
and threw Spears at him and they turned
into flowers and landed on him and then
he got enlightened that's all a
fake okay it's not true that isn't how
he got enlightened he was enlightened
before he got to this planet okay that
was all like a show to help people it's
not the real story
okay the real story is
awesome and it's in the scriptures but
you have to know where to look and
nobody's translated it
mostly uh but on the night before his
Enlightenment uh he reached a a subtle
obstacle he couldn't get through a
sudden subtle obstacle
okay and then they he got stuck and then
all the Buddhas of the universe had they
they assembled you know mentally they're
all talking to each other how are we
going to help this guy he's going to be
the next Buddha but he's got this
obstacle he's got to get over this
obstacle what what can we do to help him
then somebody said he needs a partner he
needs a spiritual partner you know he's
got to have a partner she will get him
to Enlightenment you know that will
bring him over the what do you call over
the top and they they engaged the Holy
Angel called tillotama okay you can
check it out sometime t i l o t t a m a
okay
they they proposed an enlightened being
called well she wasn't quite enlightened
okay to L and they brought her and then
he meditated together with her all night
where and in the morning they got
enlightened together and that's the real
story okay that's a beautiful story okay
uh and then those seeds were uh pure
those were done with
knowledge and then that body will never
finish you that
that that's a kind of being that's not
inside the wheel but is outside the
wheel and then you see him outside the
wheel in the picture right he's in the
upper right he's not in the wheel
anymore then those of you who know that
be that became
institutionalized in the Wongs
as the shab yesik Wang the third
empowerment okay that night became
institutionalized in the empowerments
granted in in our
lineage uh and that's where it came from
and that was the first one it's very
beautiful okay uh so anyway that's all I
have to
say
uh I think we'll do questions answer
don't embarrass me in front of Swami G
and sit there like a kafa
okay like ask some profound questions
okay uh so you can only answer two of
your homework questions from what I just
said two of them you can answer that are
just linguistic
stuff and then there'll be one more
which is about the four seals and that
you can't answer yet okay so about the
four seals leave it for tomorrow so the
two questions you answer from the
reading two questions you answer from
what I just said okay you're not out of
your your
homework okay so Swami G you
ready
so we'll tag
team we have about half an hour
something 20
minutes me
choose you choose choose good luck
okay loud question for um could you
about the tradition of celibacy in your
lineage and um your own struggle with
that and um the benefits of it and why
and where are
you it's a tough question
H do you want did anybody hear it do you
want to we should repeat it okay so the
question is uh how is celibacy perceived
in our
tradition and uh
how I dealt with any of the problems
with that and the benefits of benefits
of of
celibacy okay so I think the cibus is
uh it's it's one of the vatas or the
vows taken in all Traditions uh where
people become
monks uh it's called brahmacharya the
same in Tibetan or
yeah but the the meaning of bachara
means to to have the conduct that leads
to Brahman ideally when you say
somebody's a brahmachari it means the
one who's already realized that that
would be the highest definition of it
and then we always have like a multi-
definitions for different types of uh
people so brahmachary is the conduct
that leads to the highest realization
and one of the uh wonderful vows is
brahmacharya that can be taken either by
monks which means for life or by
partners for a little bit of a time this
is really a huge subject but the main
benefit is as you know in Raja yoga
sutras is that the one gains the an
incredible energy to accomplish the work
that will take somebody several
lifetimes he or she can do it in one
lifetime that's the that's the true
benefit of it now of course the
brahmachari in now tradition has a an
aspect that is related to celibacy and
also an aspect that is related to
controlling of all senses so there's a
story in the ram I don't know how many
people know about this and in Ramana
hanaman who is the monkey god he is the
only one who can fly over to Sri Lanka
to liberate
SAA and he was a very well-known
celibate and all other monkeys when they
were trying to jump over into Sri Lanka
they will fall into the ocean but he was
the only one who could actually go over
and the symbolism of this is that the
the Sri Lanka stands for the unconscious
mind and when he when he goes there and
he finds s he sets the whole Lan on fire
which is kind of similar like burning of
all of the karmic seeds and he could do
it through the power of His Chastity and
many stories ex examplify this in my
opinion brahmachary is more equivalent
to to the term of Vaga because vagya
means to to have not just a
nonattachment but not to be able to be
pulled in any of the direction of the
five
senses so vagi you know the word which
means
nonattachment so a brahmachari who is
just abstaining from sexual conduct but
yet is involved in engaging all his
senses and all ways is not truly
brahmachari so in a traditional yoga is
they're very strict rules and you have
to kind of go for a long time with your
teacher you have to have a guru for this
also because otherwise if you try to do
it on your own you'll find excuses for
not wanting to follow it and then you
may be you know the people become
Fanatics and and then the very celibacy
becomes the objective of the spiritual
work which is you know the means of
confused with the ends and the celus is
only the means so there are many
benefits one is health benefits bit so
we have different Pros in our system and
there is something which is called OES
and I think in Chinese medicine they
call Jing and we're born with a certain
amount of OES which is the certain
amount of energy that is in your heart
in fact this is like the a drops I think
that we talked about similar things and
this ores gets destroyed through
excessive sexual
activity so the idea is that again this
this energy is
transmuted from raw energy like a raw
material is transmuted into a very
subtle spiritual force that has a
protective effect on your aura and you
know for the spiritual work it
strengthens your nadis do you know nadis
the word the energy channels so that
they can withstand the higher pressure
of the energy movement so that's kind of
one of the reasons with prachara was
like that
taken uh um many many more benefits I
think uh the problem with the with this
kind of vow is that the sexual desire is
not perceived as Sin but it's very
difficult for us to handle it safely and
this is why you have to have a guru for
this and you when you take the vows you
take them in front of your Guru so that
you even the guru is not going to check
you with with his secret cameras or
anything like this but but you will know
that that he is connected with you on a
psychic level on a spiritual level so
that he will help you also when you
attempt it and needless to say that this
is one of the most difficult things to
deal with I mean this just remains with
you Swami vishna was very open about
this and it says there's no Yogi who did
not have problems with it and in fact
sometimes when you kind of move in that
direction you experience the full force
of that that energy and for this reason
you need to have you need to take the
vows you need to have a particular type
of life and a diet and everything
because this force is just totally out
of hand with most people and it takes a
lot of skill and a lot of humil to to
handle it so in our teachings we also
had another dimension I think this is
kind of a dedication to Lama for us is
also Devotion to Guru and to the Lord so
the devotion plays an an incredible role
here because the brahmaa even though he
addresses the Sexual Energy we say that
Sexual Energy is the part of the
Kundalini energy that is the energy of
the whole creation and all the creative
work arises from the same place the same
Energy may take the form of physical
beings where babies are born in their
way or emotion let's say Aesthetics you
know different artworks or philosophy pH
so everything is the result of this this
energy being uh transformed in a proper
way and you can see even with athletes
and a sportsman and everybody they take
temporary kind of vows for maybe
whatever weeks or months or so in order
to be able to condense that energy in a
certain way so we do also certain
practices in yoga that they help this
the bundles are done but in our
teachings in our school the bonders are
not done freely so when you come to she
one in the class we don't teach bundas
because the bundas reverse the ordinary
flow energy they need to be handled
again
properly and um I I know that the
different schools and the different
reasons why they teach them but for the
transformation of this energy bundles
are necessary as I said food is
necessary we do some little
visualizations and things like this but
um in traditionally you know in India
brahmachari is called the 100 monkey
men sh kapaya which means kapaya which
means that you have to be busy all the
time they keep you busy like a horse you
know you wake up in the morning the guru
says what did you do this okay then you
go and you run like this because it's
very easy for the mind to to get
distracted And Then There Are Rules also
which is sometimes tough for westerners
we have to have a little different
approach to it I think otherwi we would
be every was scared to death yeah what
what would you can can we ask Lama
Michael GHA to share some of his views
on this that would be wonderful uh it's
I don't know it's good for me to hear
that Swami Vishnu said every Yogi had
trouble with it I had trouble with it it
was difficult and uh oh I skip the
question all together yeah yeah
I'm it was hard for me cuz I grew up I
wasn't a lot of monks go in the
monastery when they're seven or eight
and they've never had relations with a
lady you know I I became a monk at 30
and uh I went to the monastery at 22 or
something and then I was celibate since
then but uh it was hard and I think what
Swami G said uh that I would agree with
especially is that I lived with my
teacher so if I had a problem with
masturbation or something like that
then I would go to I had to go to him
and tell him and then he was a tough
oldfashioned llama you know and he would
really you know beat on me not
physically once in a while uh no one
just once uh but uh it was so
embarrassing to tell him that I had
slipped in that way uh I never slipped
in another with a person but I I it was
very embarrassing to tell him and then
that forced me to keep it better and uh
the embarrassment of having to admit it
to him uh made it made me later able to
keep it uh well so I think I agree that
uh to have a
llama around all the time uh it's what
Swami G said you take vows in front of
the llama and then hopefully you live
close to them so that you can
confess to them when you have a weakness
and then they help you and they guide
you and I don't think you could do it on
your own uh but the results of it is
endless energy for me it's always been
um
extraordinary levels of energy and I can
work you know I can work just about
constantly well I worked in the car all
the way up and downtown and then I
worked uh we went to a lecture I did all
your homeworks in the back of the
lecture
and you just have extraordinary energy
you know and uh also I think
uh one advantage if you're a spiritual
teacher if you can keep
celibacy is
that uh people can trust you uh people
of the opposite sex especially people
can sense if you're keeping it well or
not people are people have a good
nose and uh
so if you're a male or you're
teaching uh ladies or if you're a lady
and you're teaching men and if you're
keeping your celibacy they can smell it
and then they trust you more so you're
not uh you don't have any ulterior
motives when you're talking to a woman
and they can feel it and uh then they're
more open to to to share their needs
with you because they know you're not
going to take advantage of them so I
think
uh you know if you can keep it it's it's
really sweet and I think you need a
llama to keep it so
yeah
lady
yes
absolutely of course it's important it's
for both and for men and women
um in our teachings we say that the
woman is eight times more powerful than
a man on that
level so you can can contemplate what it
means of course the if if a woman in
fact can have the control over her
energy like this she would be she she
will go faster than a
man in a spiritual in a spir in a
spiritual
domain so yeah for everybody brahmachari
brahmacharini is the same so anybody the
many many swaminis and Ladies of course
in the most modern Indian
we have more uh ladies that that the
swamis but in olden times it was
primarily men's
job but I think things have
changed yeah I will just add to do
another thing is that the prachar can
give you a tremendous
memory and this is necessary in
spiritual teachings which you have to
memorize the text you have to memorize
the practices and you have to memorize
your past lifetime sometimes you know
have to do all these things so the
health one energy another
accomplishments you know you're speeding
up your Evolution so you have to
understand when you keep this vow even
for a little time you have to understand
why you're doing it you have to have a
purpose to it and not make that goal
becomes the only objective and then you
become um you know a fanatic and then
you think all day long just how to save
yourself from ladies or how to save
yourself from Men man of course in the
west I think it's quite difficult to do
it because there's a certain Freedom
even the way how we addressed and how we
approach to one another is much more
difficult than in the East but having
said this everybody has problems East
and
West we've seen enough of
that I how this ladies just raised their
hand
yes yeah um so I'll repeat the question
uh in in our tradition you have to have
a direct experience of Ultimate Reality
in hang
on only llama has this phone
number
okay uh so I have to
answer so she said um in our tradition
it's impossible to remove a CL
without understanding Ultimate Reality
and without seeing it directly it's not
possible it's part of the definition of
nirvana
right means as a result of a direct
experience of Ultimate Reality it's the
only way you can stop your negative
emotions permanently you can suppress
them but you can't stop
them then uh Rebecca's question was you
know we keep getting angry and every
time we get angry we plant more seeds to
get angry so how are you ever going to
get over the anger because you have to
be
semi patient to see emptiness
directly okay it's a catch 22 you can't
see emptiness directly without getting
rid of your anger and you can't get rid
of your anger without seeing emptiness
directly okay then I think the easiest
answer and I think Swami G would agree
in both of our traditions and I think
it's the beauty of our Traditions both
of them
uh we share more things than we don't
share I think um it's the blessing of
your teacher okay so you must win uh you
must have a teacher you must have a
close teacher and if they're not close
you go to them okay you don't get
attached to a place you know I asked his
Holiness in
73 something like that who should I
study with you know and he said you go
to gesi Tarin and I'm like where does he
live okay so I was surfing in delmare
California he said New
Jersey I said in my mind I said the
armpit of the nation that's in in
delmare that's what they call New Jersey
and we see people from New Jersey they
come up in black cars and they're
looking out the window to to see if a
cloud will go over the Sun and then uh
if it does they come out of their car
and they look all pasty white you know
and you're like and then his hoess said
New Jersey and I'm
like you know and then you go so I lived
there I don't know for 25 years with him
in the same house and uh it's only the
blessing of your I think close contact
with you with whoever your heart teacher
is you have to drop whatever you're
doing and go be with them and stay close
to them and then the that's the blessing
that can break the
cycle otherwise it's almost impossible
because you got to stop your anger to
see emptiness but you got to see
emptiness to stop your anger and it's
almost impossible so there has to be
some
outside blessed force that that breaks
the cycle I and I I don't think it's
ever anything else than your teacher
blessing I agree I just would like to
add one more
thing that's when you're working with
any negative quality like this just by
being becoming aware of it and working
with this is an acquisition it's not a
loss so if you look at it like there was
one sage and somebody came to him and he
said I would like to lead a spiritual
life but my life is full of let's say
claes right I my life is full of uh
obstacles and difficulties and I say
what should I do and then the sage told
him uh there is no path outside of the
obstacles your obstacles are the path
you know and it's like it's a good way
of approaching it so you don't need to
look at the ultimate solution right now
but it's it's the way for you to move
towards getting your Lama and anchoring
yourself to
it
okay sorry I just saw his head first
guitarist
yes to that's what really Guru Guru
disciple relationship is
about it's
so it's everything you know it's the
guru is somebody that can see you even
if he is not in a physical form anymore
and if you're know her he doesn't need
anything any medium for that what really
is necessary because you cannot see that
directly is to to to cultivate the faith
and this is something that is almost
miraculous some people seem to have that
Faith easily some people don't and I
think comes from a Karma so that's where
you're serving the guru or llama you're
creating the merits for that experience
to become real for you so Shakti paath
of course is the path in initiations
when you receive any initiation from
your Guru it's a shaki path it's a trans
transfer of the shaki Shak of the guru
when you take the vows with the guru he
is empowering you to do certain things
but also he protecting you by the power
that he's given you for example to be a
monk you have to not just be good reader
and a practitioner but also the teacher
has to make sure that you have strength
enough to resist that The Temptations
they're going to come your way and
they're going to come your way 100 times
stronger than to an ordinary person and
naturally you know some people don't
make it and then Swami wish used to say
if you don't make it in this lifetime it
takes many many lifetimes to make a good
Swami a good
llama you know so you just have to have
faith not to say that you cannot do this
in one lifetime but I'm you know it is
kind of a shy P you
think oh the gentlemen here with the
book we have to see the
copy
gu
question what is
theing
a very good question question yeah this
is a DOA question uh If U this gentleman
saying that he seemed to have a good
innate capacity to balance his
doas uh you know the kafa the P and
nevat so
um that's the first part as as far as I
understand the second part is more like
how to whether these
does inherent in us in a way that uh
what do we need to do to be balanced
that this is kind of cutting through the
question does the balance come by itself
or do we have to make some effort to do
it so um the does are part of our prity
our nature in fact the does Z procity
there's two things there a procity and
vicity procity means that which you were
born with which is certain tendences of
course it's related to your
karmas and uh there's when these does
come out of the balance they call vicity
and sometimes when you're out of balance
it looks like that's your
nature and uh usually people are not
always sure what to do so you need to
have like somebody look at you and and
diagnos you well tell you what you doas
are predominant and so on so I think the
the whole idea of keeping the does in a
balance is to use your discrimination in
a correct way because most of the
diseases the problems and addictions are
the result of of misusage of under usage
of the discriminative power so as you
said sometimes you feel like you want to
sit in the back and be quiet and that's
what you just feel it's the right thing
to do so you're really following um I
wouldn't call it like an instinct I
prefer to use the word some kind of a
minor intuition not necessarily the
highest intuition but it's to follow
your heart and you know exactly what to
do but sometimes things are difficult
for example you may have some PA some
some kind of tendency to anger but not
very strong but then you live with
another person who has strong anger
strong P it can imbalance your P so that
requires some kind of adjustment on your
part Maybe
not be with them too much or maybe go
out for a walk or something like this
certainly do not marry a person like
this so like know because what happens
is you have to you have to kind of be
have the closest of the friends or
somebody that has some compatibility in
terms of does with you let's say a kafa
person doesn't like much of activity so
if Ka person sits with a V who is like a
bird you know cover person won't even
notice anything but the water people
will just bother them all the time why
don't you move why don't you move why
don't you
move so it's it's I think it's the the
all diseases that come as a result of
the does coming out of the balance the
result of of as I said of a
miscomprehension of of the reality and
in this case translating in a more
practical way not using one one
discriminative power properly let's say
if it's cold outside but you go with a
you know with a t-shirt that's kind of
where your discrimination is failing and
it should be warm and a warm place you
should be and most people kind of should
know this but a lot of people don't
especially when you're young you think
oh I can just do another time and you
know so there's many layers of of uh
answers there I
think I think one one more we're a
little bit over yeah
sorry he
just
Elin I don't know like from what point
of view you okay uh
I'm trying to think about fear and
what's the Tibetan word for fear and uh
how we talk about
fear
uh I I in in our tradition fear is
mostly used as a positive thing you know
like uh we had a moment maybe 45 minutes
ago I was is talking about how you might
become a dog in in a in a few minutes
and you wouldn't remember what you were
before and then I felt a little wave of
fear go through the room and we think
that's healthy we think that kind of
fear is healthy because it makes you
want to plant better seeds you see I
mean you might be a better person if you
believed that in five minutes
you could become a dog because of seeds
that are already in your mind you see I
mean nobody has to kill you and take
your spirit and put you in a body a
different body right so that I think in
our tradition uh
fear is often used as a as a motiv
motivation but I
think
uh in as you go higher in your teachings
then fear has to be replaced by
compassion uh as a motivation uh I think
that's what you you mean uh
n so I'm thinking uh it's like that yeah
in as time goes on your uh
motivation will change and I'm thinking
in this course we will shift okay
tonight let's do it now it's a good
point uh uh I'm not trying to get rid of
jealousy anymore I'm going to try to
cultivate joy in other people's
accomplishments you know when I see a a
good teacher who might threaten
me uh then I will uh no rather than Envy
I will think uh that's cool he's really
cool you know and uh let's do that to
tonight okay so tomorrow we'll start
talking
about rather than saying let's fight
anger because I'm afraid of what it will
do to me how about we say I'll become a
person who has ultimate patience with
everybody let's make it positive I think
at some point I respond better to uh
positive in my work okay so I work in a
corporation for I don't know 20 years
and uh the owner he's Israeli guy and he
was so tough on me one night I I went to
him I said I have to go home early I'm
going home early from now on I'm not
staying after 1:00
a.m. and uh he got very angry you know
it was like that you know and then
slowly I got it to 12 and then 11 and 10
and then I was going home at 5:00 and I
said fire me I'm going home at 5:00 you
know just fire me if you don't like it
fire me and then um he used to scream
and rant and I'd say I have to go to see
my teacher I have to go for my classes
you know I have to go and then um he
screamed and he yelled and then I
threatened me and then finally I just
got trto in tibetan called Tre tto means
I'm say okay fire me I don't care you
know and then one day he calls me and he
says he says we have a big order you
know we need you there's nobody in the a
company like you you're the only one who
can save us tonight you know you know
you are the man you know you are the one
who can save the company and I'm like
yeah you know I it's me you know and he
says can you stay till 11: I'm like I'll
stay till 1 you know and then so I think
uh I think uh so from tonight we'll
change it from we'll switch over from
Fear to uh let's let's make we have to
at some point we have to make it a
positive uh fight the claure by
developing its opposite and I I say
something that I I'll repeat something I
said last night my biggest problem is
jealousy and there's a special kind of
jealousy in tibetan it's called PQ say p
PQ means professional Dharma teacher
jealousy and it's a there's a word for
it okay it's the jealousy that you have
for another teacher once you start
teaching like a yoga teacher who's
jealous of another yoga teacher and
there's a special word for that in
tibetan but in my experience if you can
break through your jealousy and invite
Swami G and play music together and hang
out together and enjoy Swami G the
person who was jealous before becomes
capable of Greater Joy than people who
were never jealous you see what I mean
person who was
angry and has overcome that anger they
become a more patient person than
someone who never had a problem with
anger so I can enjoy Swami G more than
you
do uh no cuz I'm so good at jealousy so
I know no but then you can uh what I'm
saying is uh that's so let's stop the
fear tonight and you know stop thinking
I'm a jealous person the the person who
was most jealous when they fight that
cliche and beat it becomes
more uh what do you call it celebrating
of other people's talents than than the
person who never had a problem with
jealousy okay ex-alcoholics are the best
teachers about substance abuse you know
people who've never had an alcoholic
problem are not very good
counselors the people who who got over
alcoholism are the best teachers uh for
alcoholics
right B uh can you Le this in some kind
of final chat can yes surely should we
have guar so can we have a guitar I
think just here I don't need can you do
yeah okay he needs his
guitar something soft up to you you
do
he can I give
[Music]
this
just recently we had a shivaratri I
don't know if you know about this this
is a very
wonderful um celebration of L sha
symbolically there was a marriage of L
Shiva and Shakti and then we chant all
night long we do some pues there's a a
sweet chant I hope you'll like
[Music]
[Applause]
it
Nam
[Music]
nam
[Applause]
Nam
[Music]
[Applause]
nam
[Music]
[Applause]
nam
nam nam
[Music]
nam
[Applause]
[Music]
nam
[Applause]
[Music]
nam
[Applause]
[Music]
nam
[Applause]
[Music]
nam
[Applause]
[Music]
nam
[Applause]
[Music]
Nam
[Applause]
[Music]
Nam
[Applause]
I just want to say thank you very much
to all of you for your patience and um I
really am very honored that you invited
me I feel it's very
special um I don't know what else to say
you're most welcome to come to the
Bahamas to finish up your clasher
killing and uh and I will say that you
really really very lucky to have a
wonderful teacher like l m home thank
[Laughter]
you